This דף Daf is דף כ"ה Daf Kaf Hey where a drop
behind cannot be a problem. We pick up middle of כ"ד עמוד
ב'. Kaf Daled Amud Bet. We dealt with a challenging גמרא Gemara
yesterday that it was we did at the end, we didn't really
have the time to fully unpack, at least emotionally, but about the
whole issue about death of small children and the distinction between the
facts of laws of אבילות, Avelus, which begin even at after a
child is considered viable, sometimes at birth, sometimes after thirty days, but
more public aspects of mourning which deal with sort of the community,
you know, which draw which are something which are partly the community's
responsibility and becomes issues, you know, about somebody who has yet to
be known as a even as a person to the community. So
those were some very sensitive issues there, but now we resume with
the issues about the רגל Regel and how the רגל Regel interrupts.
So there was some debate about שבועות, Shavuos, is that considered is
considered a רגל Regel post-חורבן? Churban? There's a question an issue about
ראש השנה Rosh Hashana and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and the פסק
Psak basically is that all of these are considered to be רגלים
Regalim and they're מפסיק Mafsik the אבילות. Avelus. So now we pick
up with three lines down on the wide lines, beginning of the
line: דרש רב ענני בר ששון אפתחא דבי נשיא. Darash Rav Annani
bar Sasson A-pitcha de-bei Nasi.
So he explicated the following
thing on the doorstep of the בית הנשיא: Beis HaNasi: יום אחד
לפני עצרת ועצרת הרי כאן ארבעה עשר. Yom echad lifnei Atzeres ve-Atzeres
harei kan arba asar. So if you have one day before שבועות
Shavuos and then you have שבועות, Shavuos, that counts now as fourteen
days. Why? Because the שבועות Shavuos hit, so that's the end of
שבע, Sheva, and then the חג Chag of שבועות Shavuos itself, as
we know רגל Regel is עולה Oleh for the שלשים, Shloshim, so
here we have a new strange הלכה Halacha that if רגל Regel
is עולה Oleh for the שלשים, Shloshim, the concept of רגל Regel
is an idea of seven, even without, you know, because of the
idea of תשלומים Tashlumin etc. So רגל Regel is seven. So therefore
even though there was not actually seven days, it counts as seven
days because of the having gone through the רגל, Regel, that counts
as seven days towards the שלשים. Shloshim. And therefore the person only
has another sixteen days left of observance.
Where are we? Okay. שמע רבי אמי ואיקפיד. Shama Rabbi Ami ve-ikpid.
רבי אמי Rabbi Ami heard and he was he took he was
upset. Now, he wasn't upset because it was the wrong הלכה, Halacha,
but here's why he was upset. אמר, Amar, he said: אטו דידיה?
Atu didei? Wait a minute. You think, you know, you're saying this
in the name of רב, Rav, I mean not in the name
of רב, Rav, you're saying it in your own name, רב ששון?
Rav Sasson? Is this your own teaching? רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושיה!
Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya! It's רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar in the
name of רבי אושיה. Rabbi Oshaya. What are you doing saying it
in your own name? Okay. דרש רבי יצחק נפחא אקילעא דריש גלותא.
Darash Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha A-kila de-Reish Galusa. Now רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi
Yitzchak Nafcha expounded on the doorstep of the ריש גלותא. Reish Galusa.
So before it was the בית הנשיא, Beis HaNasi, here's the ריש
גלותא. Reish Galusa. אפתחא דכילתא? A-pitcha de-kila?
פתחא Pitcha is door, the כילא Kila I believe is like the
doorstep or like the, what's it called? What's that called? Not a
doorstep. It's a pavilion. Pavilion? Okay, that's thanks for the correction.
Any temporary structure built from screens or panels.
Okay, that's thanks for the correction. יום אחד לפני עצרת ועצרת הרי
כאן ארבעה עשר. Yom echad lifnei Atzeres ve-Atzeres harei kan arba asar.
Same idea. One day before שבועות Shavuos and שבועות, Shavuos, that already
counts as fourteen days. שמע רב ששת ואיקפיד. Shama Rav Sheshes ve-ikpid.
And רב ששת Rav Sheshes heard, and he also got upset. Okay.
So why? אמר: אטו דידיה? Amar: Atu didei? What, you think this
is your own teaching? רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושיה! Rabbi Elazar amar
Rabbi Oshaya! רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar in the name of רבי אושיה.
Rabbi Oshaya. דאמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושיה. D’amar Rabbi Elazar amar
Rabbi Oshaya. From where שבועות Shavuos יש לה תשלומין כל שבעה? Yesh
lah tashlumin kol shiva? So now it's a little bit more expounded.
How do you know that עצרת, Atzeres, that שבועות, Shavuos, has
for all seven days, six days after שבועות Shavuos a person can
make up the קרבנות Korbanos that he should have brought on שבועות,
Shavuos, שנאמר: Shene'emar: בחג המצות ובחג השבועות ובחג הסוכות. Be'chag HaMatzos u'vechag
HaShavuos u'vechag HaSukkos. מה חג המצות יש לו תשלומין כל שבעה, Ma
Chag HaMatzos yesh lo tashlumin kol shiva, the same way פסח Pesach
is a seven days, and seven days to bring the קרבנות, Korbanos,
אף חג השבועות יש לו תשלומין כל שבעה. Af Chag HaShavuos yesh
lo tashlumin kol shiva. So שבועות Shavuos has תשלומים Tashlumin all seven.
Now, that is not that is not connecting any dots to that
to אבילות Avelus and anyway, you know, it would be one, you
know, the idea that in that one day it counts as seven,
it's one thing if you say that one can naturally derive from
this idea that the six days following שבועות Shavuos have a special
status, I don't know, you don't say תחנון. Tachanun. Okay, fine. Those
are the actual days that you could have brought a קרבן חגיגה
תשלומים Korban Chagiga tashlumin for what you didn't bring on the חג.
Chag. But to say that the one day of שבועות Shavuos has
wrapped in it the quantity of seven days to count for אבילות
Avelus is nowhere can I see a direct derivation from this teaching.
But nevertheless what they are saying is is that that's his teaching,
you shouldn't have said it in your own name. So why where's
the first story made it sound like
רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושיה Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya explicitly said
this rule about אבילות, Avelus, here we're hearing that he didn't explicitly
say the rule, or at least in this version he didn't explicitly
say the rule, he said a other הלכה Halacha by שבועות Shavuos
that now they are saying like it was implicit in that teaching
or you should have at least given credit to that teaching as
being part of what this is all about, yes, just to me,
yes.
That's more problematic. In other words, it's less problematic like okay, he
doesn't directly say that it's a הלכה halacha in אבלות, aveilus, but
you could see where it could be derivative.
But then someone comes along and is upset because he didn't say
something בשם אומרו beshem omro when it's a derivative?
Right. That's exactly that. I don't understand that. He, you know, either
there either the claim is is that you should have you should
have at least acknowledged that that's what it was based on, that
it was based on that teaching, even if he didn't exactly say
it or maybe, you know, the claim is that he said that
he said both things but we're only quoting the other, I don't
know. It's very unclear. All right, but anyway, that's the הלכה. halacha.
Let's take a look. אתא רב פפא לגבי אביא סבא Ata Rav
Pappa legabi Avia Sava or רב פפא לגבי אביא סבא. Rav Pappa
legabi Avia Sava. So Rav Pappa took Rav Avia Sava ודרש vedarash
and he expounded. So presumably again the reason he took Rav Avia
Sava was Rav Avia Sava served as his announcer and he expounded
the following thing. יום אחד לפני ראש השנה וראש השנה הרי כאן
ארבעה עשר. Yom echad lifnei Rosh Hashanah ve-Rosh Hashanah harei kan arba'ah
asar. One day before Rosh Hashanah and Rosh Hashanah same idea counts
as fourteen. Now this is more bizarre because Rosh Hashanah doesn't have
an idea of תשלומין כל שבעה. tashlumin kol shiva. Right. And you're
having the same idea.
Now what's only one day that's יומא אריכתא. yoma arichta.
Yeah, but still doesn't get seven days. אמר רבינא הלכך יום אחד
לפני החג וחג ושמיני שלו Amar Ravina hilkach yom echad lifnei hachag
ve-chag u-shemini shelo and this is the most fascinating הלכה halacha of
אבלות, aveilus, which I don't fascinating but anyway, the most but anyway,
one day before סוכות Succos and סוכות Succos and שמיני עצרת Shemini
Atzeres הרי כאן עשרים ואחד יום. harei kan esrim ve-echad yom. There's
twenty-one days and a person only has nine days afterwards left of
שלשים. shloshim. Because comes along סוכות Succos and it ends the שבעה,
shiva, so that's seven days less to observe of the שלשים. shloshim.
Then comes along the seven days
itself of שבועות, Shavuos, I'm sorry, I keep I'm sorry, סוכות, Succos,
I'm sorry. One day before סוכות Succos that annuls the שבעה, shiva,
so now there's only seven days taken away from the שלשים. shloshim.
Then the seven days itself of סוכות Succos and we know the
רגל regel is עולה oleh for the שלשים, shloshim, which is what
we've been talking about, that's another
fourteen. Then שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres because now we've been teaching a
one day יום טוב Yom Tov counts as seven days towards the
שלשים, shloshim, that's twenty-one. And then there's only nine days left. One
minute, let's just run to the משנה. Mishnah. So אמר ליה רב
חביבא מסורא דפרת לרבינא. Amar lei Rav Chaviva mi-Sura de-Pras le-Ravina. So
Rav Chaviva from Sura by the Euphrates said to Ravina. אמר מר
יום אחד לפני ראש השנה וראש השנה הרי כאן ארבעה עשר יום.
Amar mar yom echad lifnei Rosh Hashanah ve-Rosh Hashanah harei kan arba'ah
asar yom. So we taught above that one day before Rosh Hashanah
and Rosh Hashanah now you got fourteen days because any יום טוב
Yom Tov even not a רגל regel counts as seven days. Wild
idea.
אמר ליה אנא מסתברא כרבן גמליאל הוא דאמינא. Amar lei ana mistabra
ke-Rabban Gamliel hu de-amina.
No,
no, no, I was misquoted. I said it makes sense that the
ruling is like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that says Rosh Hashanah and
יום כיפור Yom Kippur count to be מפסיק mafsik the אבלות, aveilus,
but I never said this ruling that the that Rosh Hashanah and
יום כיפור Yom Kippur count as a full seven days, which we
have to admit is a pretty shocking position. Now, תוספות, Tosafos, the
big תוספות Tosafos because תוספות Tosafos basically says who needs this הלכה?
halacha? Who needs the הלכה halacha that Rosh Hashanah, I mean you
need the הלכה halacha about שבועות Shavuos that that counts as, you
know, that that takes to combine takes away fourteen days or סוכות
Succos with שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres combined takes away twenty-one days. But
who needs the הלכה halacha that Rosh Hashanah combined itself takes away
fourteen days? That's a completely superfluous הלכה. halacha. Why? Because what's going
to happen nine days after Rosh Hashanah? יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That'll
end the שלשים. shloshim. So who cares how many days extra Rosh
Hashanah takes away from the שלשים? shloshim? Nine days later there'll be
no שלשים. shloshim. And who needs the הלכה, halacha, though we didn't
say it, but a parallel הלכה halacha that יום כיפור Yom Kippur
let's say by parallel would take away seven more days?
And then סוכות Succos and then you'll be done with the שלשים.
shloshim. So that's what this long תוספות Tosafos is here to try
to figure out, does not have a very clear answer. You look
it up in the שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, you will not find
any הלכה halacha that Rosh Hashanah takes away fourteen days. The שלחן
ערוך Shulchan Aruch says, somebody has a day, you know, observes a
little bit before Rosh Hashanah, then Rosh Hashanah ends the שבעה shiva
and יום כיפור Yom Kippur ends the שלשים. shloshim. Or observes a
little bit before יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, יום כיפור Yom Kippur ends
the שבעה shiva and סוכות Succos ends the שלשים. shloshim. So that
really becomes a moot point. So this strange הלכה halacha that a
non רגל regel counts for seven days really is moot, but it
raises the question why the גמרא Gemara bothered to say it. Okay,
and that's sort of left for תוספות Tosafos to try to figure
out. All right, now let's go on to the next משנה. Mishnah.
Okay, so now we are, believe it or not, all this discussion
we've been having for אבלות aveilus that has lasted us for a
full week has been all on explicating one משנה, Mishnah, small משנה
Mishnah about רגלים regalim and שבת Shabbos being מפסיק. mafsik. But it
gave the גמרא Gemara an opportunity to really spread out and have
this full discussion of אבלות aveilus and now we have about two
more משניות mishnayot left. Yes, but we are finally transitioning.
Clearly seems to be like against all the explanations that either like
a psychological thing, like you need a couple days transition, you know.
Yeah, so that's always the problem that people have. I mean I
don't, you know, the גמרא Gemara is not dealing with, people find
אבלות aveilus to be, you know, extremely powerful, you know, emotionally and
psychologically and so on, but it's not like the גמרא Gemara is
sort of laying this out as a sort of self-help way of
dealing with mourning. So there is a reality, yes, it is very
difficult for people, the idea, you know, that if they with not
having an opportunity. I mean we sort of say הלכה כדברי המיקל
halacha kedivrei hameikel and sometimes it's a קולא. kula. on a million
practices, right? You want a reasonable amount, but to say like, okay,
so therefore this is going to be מבטל שבעה mevatel shiva and
this is going to be מבטל שלושים mevatel shloshim or whatever for
some people that's, it's extremely hard. They never really had a had
an opportunity to process it and to and to let it sort
of internalize it, and it can be very, very challenging, these scenarios.
There's no question about that.
But if you want to, we're not saying that it's,
yes, we are.
Oh,
we mean...
oh, after the רגל regel a person wants to still do some
self-imposed practices, you can do that. But it's אסור assur during the
רגל regel to do those practices. Okay, so let's take a look
now
at this next one.
אין קורעין ולא חולצין, Ein korin v'lo choltzin, one does not do
קריעה keriah for a death, and חליצה chalitzah does not mean here
what we'll be learning in about a month, which is in הלכות
יבמות Hilchos Yevamos about that type of a חליצה, chalitzah, but it
means
to uncover the shoulders as we've seen before. ואין מברין V'ein mavrin
and what does not do the הבראה, havra'ah, the סעודת הבראה, seudat
havra'ah, which is the serving of the meal immediately after returning from
the cemetery, which the הלכה halacha is that an אבל avel does
not eat his own food. Other people serve them, serve them their
first meal,
probably as we know, a major thing that happens during שבעה, shiva,
people send a lot of food, but anyways there's an actual הלכה
halacha that the first meal the אבל avel is fed by someone
else. אלא קרובו של מת, Ela kerovo shel meit, the only people
who do this are the immediate relatives of the of the deceased.
Okay, now, that's a very bizarre הלכה. halacha. Like, why don't you
just say you don't observe שבעה shiva and שלושים shloshim except the
immediate relatives of the deceased? So it could be because as we've
heard before and we're going to hear in a minute as we
do the גמרא, Gemara, that when a great sage dies or great
people dies, sometimes other, everybody would sort of treat it as a
as a tragedy and
and the idea of doing קריעה keriah and so on would be
something that non-relatives would do. Now, they wouldn't really do a שבעה
shiva and a שלושים, shloshim, we'll hear maybe there would be an
idea of a one-day אבילות, aveilus, but that wasn't the practice. But
the practice was that they would do some type of a of
a קריעה. keriah. So then you understand, oh, so if people are
doing קריעה keriah for non-relatives,
the משנה Mishna have to say, or חליצה, chalitzah, right, these two
immediate signs of expressions of tragedy, not an ongoing sign of mourning,
but these immediate expressions of tragedy, if that was if that was
a phenomenon the משנה Mishna have to say that don't do it,
don't do it unless you're a relative. The only problem is as
the גמרא's Gemara going to immediately turn to is, what do you
mean don't do it? That's a well-established phenomenon that people do קריעה
keriah and חליצה chalitzah for a חכם, chacham, a נשיא, nasi, and
so on. We've had some of those stories before. So it's hard
to understand, and that's, and you'll see what the what the גמרא
Gemara gets into in the answer. But that's, I would say, a
פשט peshat way of understanding this משנה, Mishna, why it says הבראה
havra'ah is not clear, but anyway that's a pretty פשט peshat way.
But a very different way of reading this משנה Mishna is the
way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi reads it, and it's read by most of
the ראשונים, Rishonim, which is, it means during חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
We're not talking about regular. We mean on
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Okay, we just got through saying that there's
no practice of אבילות aveilus during the רגל, regel, including חול המועד.
Chol HaMoed. But something like these things would be something that the
that the immediate relatives would do on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. They
would still do קריעה keriah according to this way of reading it,
and
חליצה, chalitzah, and these types of things, and the סעודת הבראה. seudat
havra'ah. Oh, but that would be limited only to the immediate relatives
and not to anyone else. That's the way the ראב"ד Ra'avad reads
it. It doesn't sound like the גמרא Gemara reads it however, but
that's the way the ראב"ד Ra'avad and the and the based on
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi reads this, that we're talking about
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. ואין מברין אלא על מיטה זקופה V'ein mavrin
ela al mitah zekufah and you only do
הבראה havra'ah on a on a upright bed, not an overturned bed,
not on a מיטה כפויה. mitah kefuyah. So again, what's the context?
If it's during the rest of the week, that's a little bit
bizarre. If it's during a normal time, so then you're supposed to
overturn your beds. So why would you say that the הבראה havra'ah
is not on an overturned bed?
So Rabbeinu Gershom here, who reads it as not on חול המועד
Chol HaMoed at a normal time, says we're not talking about the
אבל, avel, we're talking about the person feeding the אבל. avel. So
the אבל avel is on a מיטה כפויה mitah kefuyah and the
person feeding him though should be on a normal chair, not on
overturned chair. Again, the ראב"ד Ra'avad and the ראש Rosh based on
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi say the opposite in both directions. They first of
all say that the whole idea of הבראה havra'ah is that the
person feeding the אבל avel would sit directly together with the אבל
avel and in a way sort of be do a somewhat of
a join with him in that אבילות aveilus moment, sit together with
him. So first of all, denies the idea that there would be
a difference, that the אבל avel would be on a מיטה כפויה
mitah kefuyah and that the and that the feeder, the one giving
the food, would be on a מיטה זקופה. mitah zekufah. They reject
that. They actually say they'd be on the same bed, or at
least under certain circumstances, if they felt intimate enough and comfortable enough
with one another, they would actually
sit together. Well, if it's חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, what's the story
with the upturned beds in the אבל's avel's house? What do they
have to do with them for חול המועד?
Chol HaMoed?
Not supposed to upturn them, it's דברים שבפרהסיא. devarim sheb'farhesya. So therefore
it's saying that even though it's חול המועד Chol HaMoed and we've
said that the קרובים krovim do קריעה kria and do סעודת הבראה
seudat havra'a and do this חליצה, chalitza, but they're not doing other
aspects of visible mourning. So therefore the eating of the סעודה seuda
will still take place on an upright bed, on a מיטה זקופה
mitta zkufa and not on a מיטה כפויה. mitta kfuya. Okay, so
a little complicated that there are two very different ways of reading
this. One is just as a general broad statement having nothing to
do with יום טוב Yom Tov or חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, which
is, again, remember we are in מסכת מועד קטן, Masechet Moed Katan,
which is about חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So to assume that after
a short משנה, mishna, it's important also to orient ourselves in terms
of the mindset of the משנה. mishna. We've just spent all of
this enormous time immersing ourselves in הלכות אבילות. hilchot avelut. But the
משנה mishna is dropped in the middle of מועד קטן Moed Katan
which is about חול המועד Chol HaMoed without any explanation about what
we're doing having a משנה mishna about it, although the משנה mishna
is primarily about רגלים, regalim, so רגלים regalim and חול המועד Chol
HaMoed are, you know, wherever, they sort of come together and רגלים
regalim being מפסיק. mafsik. And so to say then that the next
משנה mishna is getting us after having talked briefly about רגלים regalim
in the משנה, mishna, not in the גמרא Gemara about רגלים regalim
and אבילות, avelut, we're now going to get back to our natural
context of חול המועד Chol HaMoed and that this משנה mishna is
now talking about practices during חול המועד Chol HaMoed is a pretty
reasonable explanation once we realize, take ourselves out of the גמרא Gemara
and realize the context of מועד קטן. Moed Katan. So that's one
way of reading it. The other way of reading it is no,
we're still deep in הלכות אבילות, hilchot avelut, this is not about
חול המועד Chol HaMoed and this is a general statement all the
time. So again, according to the חול המועד Chol HaMoed read, the
ruling is, is that although there are not practices during חול המועד
Chol HaMoed of שבעה, shiva, there are some שלושים shloshim practices we
know, but anyway there's not שבעה, shiva, there are not practices of
אבילות, avelut, these practices of קריעה kria and חליצה chalitza and סעודת
הבראה seudat havra'a would be done, but they can only be done
by קרובים, krovim, but if they're being done, they have to be
done on an erect, upright bed because you're not having the upturned
beds on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So that's one way about what
can you do on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, what small practices are
allowed but only allowed for קרובים. krovim. The other reading is has
nothing to do with חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Don't do קריעה, kria,
don't do חליצה chalitza for anybody who is not a relative, because
there was practices to do it for other people even non-relatives. And,
by the way, getting back to other הלכות אבילות, hilchot avelut, when
serving the סעודת הבראה seudat havra'a to an אבל avel and the
אבל avel is on the upturned bed, you should be on an
upright bed, okay? So two very different ways of what this משנה
mishna is talking about.
That was more for vocabulary, the word מיטה. mitta. Sometimes it means
bed, sometimes it means
chair.
Yeah, I've been saying bed, but I should have stopped and clarified
because all this thing about eating on it and sitting on it,
we're talking more about like a couch and the couch people would
recline on the couch when they would eat and they would, so
it's much more here about a couch then, right? And Michael asked
the other day, why is upturn the מיטה mitta דברים שבפרהסיא, devarim
sheb'farhesya, who's going into my bedroom? So here really it much more
is like a divan or like a couch or something like that,
yeah.
So, you didn't, we didn't see that the אבל avel is אסור
asur to the first meal
he eats during שבעה? shiva?
No, he's not אסור asur to cook.
Right, but the
הלכה halacha is the first meal he's supposed to be fed from
other people's food and not his.
And when we say קרוב, karov, well it has to be someone
close enough that he's not mourning, because otherwise he'd be sitting too,
so someone else has to come. So it has to be like
some sort of slightly more distant close
friend, or a close friend.
But קרובים krovim doesn't necessarily mean a relative?
No, no, no, what do you mean? אין מברין אלא... Ein mavrin
ela... no, מברין mavrin here, yes. So according to רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu
Gershom, the word מברין mavrin means two different things in this line
of the משנה. mishna. The first מברין mavrin means to be fed
the סעודת הבראה seudat havra'a and the second מברין mavrin means to
feed the סעודת הבראה. seudat havra'a. Okay, also very confusing, which again,
if we're talking about חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, it's consistent. It means
the person that's eating the סעודת הבראה seudat havra'a is only a
relative on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, and when he eats it though,
he eats it on an upright couch, not on an upturned couch,
again because it's חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Okay, so yes, that's, that's
a good point to make, that מברין mavrin according to רבנו גרשום
Rabbeinu Gershom means exactly two different things.
Does it say that then basically that's it, but so someone who's
not necessarily an אבל avel and he has to be sitting on
a low chair or whatever it is, that's what we do now,
so...
no, we don't do that now, but according, again, but according to
the ריב"ן Riban and the רא"ש, Rosh, ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, whatever, they actually
would, if you felt close enough to the אבל, avel, would actually
for that first meal sit together with him. Okay, let's take a
look now at the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara ignores the
possible חול המועד Chol HaMoed read of this משנה. mishna. It doesn't
say one way or the other, but seems to ignore it and
seems to see it as a general statement that you don't do
קריעה kria for somebody who is not a relative. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואפילו חכם? V'afilu chacham? You
wouldn't do קריעה kria even on a חכם, chacham, even on a
sage if you weren't a relative? והתניא, V'hatanya, we saw in a
ברייתא, braita, חכם שמת הכל קרובו. Chacham shemet hakol krovo. When a
חכם chacham dies, everybody is his relative. הכל קרובו סלקא דעתך? Hakol
krovo salka datcha? What, literally everybody's his relative? אלא הכל כקרובו. Ela
hakol k'krovo. All right, everybody's like his relative. Now back to the
ברייתא braisa, *beraita*. That was the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s sort of interjection.
But here's the ברייתא braisa, *beraita*: הכל קורעין עליו *hakol kor'in alav*,
everybody has to do קריעה kria *kriya*, והכל חולצין עליו *v'hakol chotzin
alav*, everybody has to remove the, uncover the shoulder, והכל מברין עליו
ברחבה *v'hakol mavrin alav barachava*, and everybody has to eat that אבלות
avelut *aveilus* meal in the road. Now by the way, you now
understand but why would you do this and not שבעה shiva *shiva*
as a practice? Because שבעה *shiva* practices are you know are long
term. They're like a few days, they're a week and so on.
This is an immediate reaction. So an immediate reaction to show the
sense of the tragedy, you understand קריעה kria? *kriya* and חליצה chalitza
*chalitza*. But what is this about הבראה *havara*? Well הבראה *havara* is
the meal immediately after the burial. So what we're basically talking is
that here it is, this great sage dies, everybody wants to show
how tragic this is for the whole community. So everybody does קריעה
kria? *kriya*, everybody does חליצה *chalitza* presumably also as now they bring
him to the cemetery, they bury him. Everybody sits down and does
this first meal of mourning, the סעודת הבראה *seudat havara*, and then
everybody else goes on to their normal lives whereas the קרובים krovim.
*krovim* do שבעה *shiva*. So that's why it's these three of קריעה
kria *kriya*, חליצה *chalitza*, and הבראה *havara* that were done more widely.
Okay, so anyway you have a ברייתא braitah *beraita* that explicitly says
that you do it for a חכם Chacham *chacham*. Now the simple
פשט pshat *pshat* is that רבי Rebbe. *Rebbi* is actually, that the
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* is arguing on the ברייתא braitah *beraita*. It's clear
from what this ברייתא *beraita* and other things that we've read in
the past that people would do these practices for great sages. And
the simple פשט *pshat* of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* is it's saying
no, we should not be doing it for anybody who's not a
relative, just do it for relatives. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* completely
refuses to accept that read. It was so well established, this practice
of doing it for great sages and for you know great leaders
and so on, and there's clear other תנאי *Tannaic* evidence that it
was done that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* you know has a way
of just completely bracketing what our משנה Mishna *Mishnah* seems to be
saying. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says
לא צריכא דלאו חכם Chacham. הוא *lo tzericha d'lav chacham hu*. No,
the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* means if it's not a sage, only relatives
do it, except for the cases of a sage. But if it's
just a case of a normal layperson, then don't do it if
you're not a relative. Okay, ואי אדם כשר adam kasher, הוא *v'ei
adam kasher hu*, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay, but even
if he's not a sage, if he's like an upright upstanding individual,
like somebody you know who really is a model of ethical you
know behavior in the community, and everybody respects the person even if
he's not a total sage, חיובי מיחייב למיקרי *chiyuvei michayev lemikrei*? You
have to do קריעה kria *kriya*? דתניא de-tanya *d'tanya*, we taught in
a ברייתא *beraita*, מפני מה מתים meitim, בניו ובנותיו של אדם כשהם
קטנים *mipnei mah metim banav u'vnotav shel adam k'sheheim ktanim*? Talk about
cold straightness. Why does a person's sons and daughters die כשהם קטנים
*k'sheheim ktanim* when they are small, when they are still minors? כדי
שיבכה ויתאבל על אדם כשר adam kasher. *k'dei sheyivkeh v'yitabel al adam
kasher*. In order that the person should cry and mourn for an
upstanding individual when he dies. Now what does that mean? First of
all, what's the logical connection besides the whole theology? Somebody dies ahead
of time in order to make sure that when a great person
dies you'll mourn? So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אדם כשר adam kasher. *adam kasher*? שיבכה ויתאבל
*sheyivkeh v'yitabel*? In order that you should cry or that he should
cry, that he should mourn? ערבונא קשקיל מיניה *arvona kashkil mineih*? You're
taking a collateral from him? Meaning what does that mean? I'm going
to, this is going to be so in the future you do
the right thing. I mean what type of logic is that? Horrible.
I mean right, even without getting to the, to the theology like
I said, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s just trying to figure out the
logic. What's the logic of punishing somebody ahead of time? אצמכתיה נמי
*atzmachteih nami* so make sure you do the right thing later.
Well I got that עליה *aliyah* yesterday.
Okay, so anyway so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ערבונא קשקיל מיניה
*arvona kashkil mineih*? אלא מפני שלא בכה ויתאבל על אדם כשר adam
kasher? *ella mipnei shelo bacha v'yitabel al adam kasher*. It's obviously the
person did something wrong in the past and that's why he's being
punished. So maybe it means and therefore by being punished he'll do
it right again in the future. But because somebody did not do
the right thing in the past, did not appropriately acknowledge, you know,
again what does that have to do with the children dying? Look,
there's you know the already you know in the תורה Torah. *Torah*
there are you know פוקד עון אבות על בנים *poked avon avot
al banim* etc.
and while on the one hand איש בחטאו יומתו *ish b'cheto yumatu*
there certainly are also ideas of you know this sense of children
as being punished for the sins of the father, you know it's
father not parent, so also a male assumption there. And you know
to some degree also coming maybe from a sense of of children
as property, you know also is part perhaps of that whole mindset.
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sometimes reflects those understandings which are extremely
deeply disturbing. You also have to understand that you're living in a
society in which there's an enormous amount of people of children who
die young. You know, so to look for some type of explanation
of why all this happens and what did the children do to
deserve it, I'm not saying that this answer is helpful for us,
but at least you can understand where it's coming from. Now why
though exactly this sin leads to this, why didn't we say some
other sin led to it because he didn't keep שבת *Shabbat* correctly
or something, is not clear, except I would sort of suggest that
the idea is that if somebody does not... express the gravity and
the tragedy of some such a person of such great moral stature,
you know, sort of their death, then, you know, that's also an
impact in terms of what do you value in the world and
how does that translate into what you're passing down to your children?
So maybe there could be some type of a connection there, right?
It's one thing to acknowledge a sage which in terms of their
societal status is very clear. Everybody knows who the חכמים are so,
you know, everybody acknowledges that they have a position and a status
in society. Somebody who's a normal layperson, he could be the most
upright and upstanding and moral paragon, but he doesn't have any special
status in the community. He's an accountant, right? So you have to
acknowledge, you know, you have a moral obligation to acknowledge who that
person is and somebody who doesn't acknowledge who that person is maybe
doesn't have their values exactly in the right place. So I think
that could be some of what's going on here, but again, it's
a very harsh type of a statement. Okay. So let's take a
look. שכל הבוכה ומתאבל על אדם כשר Shekol haboche umisabel al adam
kasher because anybody who cries and mourns for the death of an
אדם כשר, adam kasher
מוחלין לו על כל עוונותיו. mochalin lo al kol avonosav. All of
the sins are forgiven. And again, presumably because it shows that somebody
acknowledges what the intrinsic worth of people is and not just their
status in society. בשביל כבוד שעשה לו Bishvil kavod she'asa lo because
of the honor that is done to him. So the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, so now back to our question. So look, you do
קריעה kria. for somebody who's not a קרוב. karov. So the גמרא
Gemara says, פשיטא באדם כשר עסקינן. peshita be'adam kasher askinan. It means
without the special case of an אדם כשר. adam kasher, Just a
normal person. My, you know, my friend died, חס ושלום. chas v'shalom.
You know, somebody's friend died, should they do, you know, do they
do could they do קריעה? kria. You know, my second somebody's second
cousin died. Can they do קריעה? kria. לאו אדם כשר.
lav
adam kasher.
No, no, no, no, this is not an אדם כשר. Adam kasher
Just a regular friend.
So why can't this friend be an אדם כשר?
adam kasher I'm not saying he can't. I'm saying that אדם כשר
adam kasher. is a very small number of people and the point
that the גמרא Gemara is saying is to try to reconcile these
sources is that the משנה is not talking about exceptional cases. Exceptional
cases of a חכם Chacham and an אדם כשר, adam kasher, yes,
you would do these act practices of קריעה kria and so on
and so forth. But what it means is people might have a
desire to do קריעה kria. and חליצה and so on for somebody
that is not one of these exceptional cases. Somebody that's a little
bit more of a distant relative, somebody that's a close friend. For
those type of cases, the משנה is saying no, it's only for
קרובים. krovim. But it's not meant to exclude these very special cases.
אדם כשר adam kasher I put in the same category as חכם.
Chacham, Yes. Not really sure what does what אדם כשר really means
in terms of the idea of the גמרא.
Okay, גמרא does not fully unpack it. I tried to give my
understanding of it. So the גמרא says like this. Okay. אי דקאי
התם בשעת יציאת נשמה Ee d'kai hasam b'sha'as yetzias neshama
now the גמרא says fine. So now we said the משנה is
talking about not these special cases of חכם Chacham, and אדם כשר.
But there's other cases that a person should do קריעה. kria. If
he's there when the soul passes away, קריעה בעי למיעבד kria ba'i
l'me'evad he's obligated to do קריעה. kria, דתניא דתני רב שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר detanya detane Rav Shimon ben Elazar omer העומד על המת
בשעת יציאת נשמה ha'omed al hamess b'sha'as yetzias neshama if somebody is
present when the soul actually leaves when the person dies, חייב לקרוע
chayav likroa he has to he has to do קריעה. kria למה
זה דומה L'ma ze domeh what's that similar to? לספר תורה שנשרף
L'sefer Torah shenisraf like seeing a ספר תורה sefer Torah burned, which
makes it seem like it's obvious that you would do קריעה kria
when a ספר תורה sefer Torah is burned because of the tragedy.
So there's a tragedy what at the moment that anybody dies, שחייב
לקרוע shechayav likroa that you have to do קריעה. kria, Okay, fascinating,
you know, that whole also idea, right, the soul and the the
idea of it sort of being an embodied תורה. Torah,
So anyway, the גמרא says, so there are other obligations to do
קריעה. kria דלא קאי התם בשעת יציאת נשמה. D'lo kai hasam b'sha'as
yetzias neshama. Okay, we're not talking that you were a person was
around when the person died. So there are other cases of קריעה,
kria the moment of death, being present at a moment of death,
חכם, Chacham אדם כשר,
without any of those special cases, the משנה is saying don't do
קריעה kria, for somebody who is not a relative and not talking
about the special cases, a close friend, an extended relative, no, don't
do קריעה kriya, for them. There are other cases you'll do קריעה,
kriya חכם, chacham. אדם כשר etc., but without those other but but
talking about a normal case, קריעה kriya. is only for the קרובים.
Okay, now the גמרא continues. כי
נח נפשיה דרב ספרא Ki nach nafshiah d'Rav Safra when רב ספרא
Rav Safra passed away, לא קרעו רבנן עליה. lo kara'u rabanan alei.
The rabbinic sort of students did not do קריעה kriya for him.
אמרי Amri they said, לאו גמינא מיניה. lav gaminei minei. He wasn't
our Rebbe. We didn't learn from him. אמר להו אביי Amar lehu
Abaye so אביי Abaye said to them, מי תניא הרב שמת? mi
tanya harav shemess? We didn't say the Rav, the rabbi that died,
which might suggest your Rav, חכם שמת
תניא Chacham shemess tanya a sage. So as long as he's a
sage in the community, you don't have to have the personal connection
to him. ועוד V'od right, so and that's by the way very
powerful, that means that everybody in the city has to do קריעה,
kriya it's not about a personal connection to him. ועוד V'od and
not only that, even according to your understanding that it means it
needs to be some personal connection to the to the person and
his תורה, Torah. כל יומא שמעתתיה בפומין בבי מדרשא kol yoma shmatetay
b'fumin b'vei medrasha
every day his teachings are in our
in our house of study. Ok, סברו מה דהוה הוה. savru mah
dehavah havah. So they figured alright, what was was, we missed the
opportunity, right, especially remember before our whole discussion that you need to
do קריעה בשעת חימום, kriya beshas chimun,
so they
figured alright, it was too late. So אמר להו אביי, amar lehu
Abaye, so then אביי Abaye said to them, no, תנינא, tanina, we
taught in a ברייתא, חכם כל זמן שעוסקין בהספד חייבין לקרוע. Chacham
kol zman she'oskin behesped chayavin likro'a.
As long as you're still involved in the process of eulogizing, even
if it's not immediately upon hearing about the death, you have to
do קריעה, kriya and you certainly can understand that as an expression
of כבוד. kavod. Right, by the way, it's worth noting, and we're
going to spend whatever time we have left today, we are falling
a little bit behind, but okay, the last day is only like
ten lines. But whatever, but that the הספד, hesped, the point of
the הספד hesped was not was not just to say, you know,
so to say all the wonderful things this person did and describe
their life, it actually was to stir up people's emotions and get
them to feel how tragic it was and get them to cry
and get them to mourn and wail. So there you are doing
a הספד hesped of this great sage, so that's the time to
do קריעה kriya to show how how over you know how tragic
you're feeling the event was, how overwhelmed you are, and that's the
moment of doing of doing קריעה. So as long as it's still
involved in the הספד, hesped, you're still obligated to do קריעה if
you have not done it yet. So סברו למקרע לאלתר. savru l'mikre
l'alter. They said that okay, good, so there's like two more הספדים
hespedim scheduled for later today, so we're still in the process of
הספדים. hespedim. Let's do קריעה right now because we forgot to do
it earlier or we didn't think we had to do it earlier.
אמר להו אביי, amar lehu Abaye, so אביי Abaye said to them
תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, חכם כבודו בהספדו. Chacham kevodo
behespedo. The greatest כבוד kavod is you do it at the moment
of the הספד. hesped. For what I said, not just we're still
in the immediate aftermath and it's still the right time and an
acceptable time. At at the moment of the הספד hesped you express
the sense of the you know of the tragedy of the loss
by doing קריעה at that moment. That's the that is the way
to honor the dead. By the way, Michael, that goes back to
the question about you know we postpone
קריעה till usually like till after the burial and so on and
so you know or the time
of the what do you call it of the funeral might be
somewhat connected to to this line, although really the I know it's
a חכם chacham, but I'm saying it might be somewhat connected. But
the actual real הלכה halacha is like immediate upon hearing of the
death is when there's חיוב קריעה. chiyuv kriya.
So חכם כבודו בהספדו, Chacham kevodo behespedo,
and then then they wanted to do it then and אביי Abaye
said
wait till the moment of the הספד. hesped. Don't do it now.
I mean they weren't actually doing the הספד, hesped, they were preparing.
Yeah, exactly. כי נח נפשיה דרב הונא, ki nach nafshei deRav Huna,
and when רב הונא Rav Huna died his soul passed
away, סברו לאותובי ספר
תורה אפורייה. savru l'osvei sefer Torah apurei. They wanted to put a
ספר תורה sefer Torah on his on his bed, you know, on
his in his coffin on the bed they were bringing him out.
They weren't going to bury the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, but they
wanted that when they carried him to the you know to the
cemetery he would be lying together with a ספר תורה. sefer Torah.
And we see in other גמרות Gemaros that they would do this
for great people and they would say קיים זה מה שכתוב בזה.
kiyam zeh mah shekasuv b'zeh. This person fulfilled everything written in this,
like it's like this person is a ספר תורה sefer Torah that
we are burying. Before we had every individual's like a ספר תורה
sefer Torah right but here anyway for a great sage they would
often do this as they would carry the person to the funeral
or not often but they would sometimes with a really great sage
put a ספר תורה sefer Torah to speak about like this is
like a ספר תורה sefer Torah that is lost this person fulfilled
the whole תורה. Torah So they wanted to do that with what
do you call it with רב הונא. Rav Huna. So אמר להו
רב חסדא, amar lehu Rav Chisda, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said
to them מילתא דבחיים לא סבירא ליה, milta d'bechayim lo sevira lei,
something that in his life he would not have held of, השתא
לקום וליעביד ליה hashta lekum veliyavid lei now you're going to do
it to him? How do we know? דאמר רב תחליפא, d'amar Rav
Tachlifa, because רב תחליפא Rav Tachlifa said אנא חזיתיה לרב הונא דבעי
למיתב אפורייא. ana chazisiei l'Rav Huna deba'i lemisav apurya. I saw רב
הונא Rav Huna wanted to sit here again on a bed but
here again bed meaning like a couch. He wanted to sit on
a couch והוה מנח ספר תורה עליה vehavah manach sefer Torah alei
and there was a ספר תורה sefer Torah on it וכף כדא
ארעא vechaf kada ara'a so he took some type of of a
pitcher of a vessel and turned it up on the and you
know upturned it on the ground ואותביה לספר תורה עילויה ve'osvei l'sefer
Torah iluvei and he made it like into a temporary little table
and he put the ספר תורה sefer Torah on it. So אלמא
alma you see קסבר אסור לישב על גבי מיטה שספר תורה מונח
עליה. kasavar assur lishev al gabi mita she'sefer Torah munach aleha. You
can't sit on a bed on a couch if a ספר תורה
sefer Torah is on it. So you're going to have him lie
next on you know in the same coffin with a ספר תורה?
sefer Torah? So he would never have done that in his lifetime.
So okay now that's story part one of what they were doing.
Now לא הוה, lo havah, it's going to be a long story
about what things that occurred in the process of burying רב הונא
Rav Huna after he died.
So לא הוה נפיק פורייא מבבא. lo havah nafik purya mibaba. His
bed that they were going to take him out in and maybe
even that he died on so they were going to take out
to the cemetery couldn't fit through the door. Okay ever have that
problem getting moving furniture in an apartment it might happen. Can't fit
through the door.
So סברו לשלשולי דרך גגין. savru leshishulei derech gagin. They thought oh
maybe we'll... what we could do is we could like hoist it
up to the rooftop, take it out of a window, and maybe
carry it over the rooftops, or hoist it down from a rooftop.
Okay, they sometimes do that with furniture, you know, they take it
up through some major window and they hoist it up rather than
what?
Is that a בזיון? bizayon?
Well, let's take a look. So,
אמר להו רב חסדא, amar lehu Rav Chisda, so רב חסדא Rav
Chisda says, גמירנא מיניה, gamirna minei, one minute, I learned from him,
חכם כבודו דרך פתח,
chacham kevodo derech
petach,
a sage, the way to take him out in an honorable way
is through the פתח, petach, not through some window. So okay,
סברו לאשנויי מפוריא לפוריא, savru lashunoyei mi-purya le-purya, they said fine, let's
move him onto a different like couch or bed that's narrower and
then we'll be able to take him out, right? Because the doorway
had to be like the normal width, you know, it had to
be as wide as a human being because normal people would go
in and out from it. So here he was, he died on
some king bed, you know, on a king-size bed, you couldn't take
it out. So now you want to move him onto a narrow
bed so that you can take it out of the door. What?
I'm sorry to interrupt you, yes? Why don't they move his body
out the door and the furniture out the window and then?
Well, that's essentially what they're saying, but it wouldn't be honorable to
take him out without being on something, to just carry his body
out. So they're saying put him on some other narrower piece of
furniture and take him out on that.
So that's actually really an issue, in other words, it's critical, the
כבוד kavod is connected to carrying the body on something.
Yes, I think that's the, I think that's the, right.
Oh look, alright, it doesn't mean, alright, as a normal rule, I'm
not going, anyway, so yes, but that's the assumption that you know,
just think about what would it mean to carry somebody without being
on a piece of furniture, like just you know, it seems to
me intuitive that that would not be, there's not a good way
to do that in a way that could be respectful. So anyway,
so they wanted to switch him to another piece of furniture. אמר
להו רב חסדא, amar lehu Rav Chisda, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda
said, הכי גמירנא מיניה, hachi gamirna minei, this is what I have
learned from him, חכם כבודו במטה ראשונה, chacham kevodo be-mitah rishonah,
the way of honoring him is taking him out on the first
bed, on the bed that he died in or the first bed
he was placed in after he died. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מניין לחכם שכבודו במטה ראשונה, minayin le-chacham
she-kevodo be-mitah rishonah, where do you see this? שנאמר, she-ne'emar,
fascinating comparison here also to a ספר תורה Sefer Torah as a
way, or the same idea, וירכיבו את ארון האלהים על עגלה חדשה.
vayarkivu et aron ha-elohim al agalah chadashah. So they put the עגלה
חדשה, agalah chadashah, thank you,
they put the ארון aron of God on the new wagon. So
this is the story about you know, when David retrieved the ארון,
aron, when
it had been returned from the פלשתים Pelishtim and it had been
there in
what's-his-name's house.
Somebody help me here.
אבינדב, Avinadav, you said?
אבינדב
בגבעה.
Avinadav ba-Givah.
What?
אבינדב... Avinadav... אבינדב בגבעה. Avinadav ba-Givah. No, the first time.
2 Samuel 6.
2 Samuel 6, okay. Anyway, fine. Anyway,
so yeah, אבינדב, Avinadav, that's what רש"י Rashi says also here, אבינדב.
Avinadav. So anyway, or רבינו גרשום. Rabbeinu Gershom. Anyway, they were going
to retrieve it after that you know, from where it had been
when the פלשתים Pelishtim had sent it back. And somehow again, I
don't know how they're reading this, because עגלה חדשה agalah chadashah sounds
to me like it's a new wagon. But somehow it's being read
to be understood to be the wagon that had been sent with
the פלשתים. Pelishtim. I'm not exactly sure what the derivation is, because
the פשט of the פסוק pasuk is new wagon, right? I don't
know, do they say anything?
רש"י Rashi in 2 Samuel says this, they talk about a new
wagon also.
Yeah. Oh, you mean when they sent it it was called עגלה
חדשה? agalah chadashah? Might be. Alright, fine. Anyway, somehow, somehow this is
being read, I'm sorry I didn't sort of look into that more
closely, what? When they sent it initially it's called עגלה חדשה? agalah
chadashah? Alright, anyway, don't want to take up... alright. Anyway, somehow it's
understood that this means the same wagon that it was sent with.
So again, interesting to note the comparison of the deceased to an
ארון, aron, to the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and so on, and
that's also the idea specifically again about a חכם. chacham So now
there are these two comparisons. They wanted to put the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah with them, and now the idea here about the מטה
ראשונה. mitah rishonah. Okay, but again specifically here it's חכם שכבודו במטה
ראשונה. chacham she-kevodo be-mitah rishonah. So that's also you know, interesting, like
maybe a normal person you can move from place to place, but
somehow not to overly disturb the body of the חכם, it's some
extra type of honor that is being shown, like the sort of
type of honor of a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Just think about
the הלכה, halacha, for example, that you're not supposed to move with
a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, right, from place to place unless you're
going to use it for like three days, right? People know that
הלכה. halacha.
We violate it all the time.
Right, okay, but still there's this idea of overly disturbing the ספר
תורה. Sefer Torah. So again, this here is now as opposed to
the other thing, which is about a general הלכה halacha for all
מתים, right, about the פתח petach as opposed to going through the
window, here the idea of not overly disturbing the body and moving
it from one bed to another is said about a חכם and
the comparison is made regarding the ארון. aron. Okay, פורץ בבא, poretz
bava, so they basically knocked down the door. What else were they
able to do? They had to demolish the door. ואפקוה ve'afkuei and
they took him out. Okay, so that's how they finally solved it.
Now, פתח עליה רב אבא, patach alei Rav Abba, so now רב
אבא Rav Abba opened the following type of a, like a eulogy
and now the גמרא is going to shift into a fascinating thing
about like eulogies that would be said for the deaths of different
of different great sages. So פתח עליה רבי אבא, patach alei Rabbi
Abba, ראוי היה רבינו, rauy haya Rabbeinu, our Rabbi רב הונא Rav
Huna was fit שתשרה עליו שכינה shetishreh alav Shechina that the Divine
Presence should rest on him אלא שבבל גרמה ליה ela she-Bavel garma
lei it was because he was in בבל Bavel like and the
Divine Presence does not rest on, you know, people in בבל Bavel
only in people in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So מתיב רב נחמן
בר חסדא, metiv Rav Nachman bar Chisda, רב נחמן בר חסדא Rav
Nachman bar Chisda challenged this, ואמרי לה רב חנא בר חסדא, ve'amri
lah Rav Chana bar Chisda, some say רב חנא בר חסדא, Rav
Chana bar Chisda, but it says היה היה דבר השם אל יחזקאל
בן בוזי הכהן בארץ כשדים, haya haya devar Hashem el Yechezkel ben
Buzi ha-Kohen be-eretz Kasdim, right, יחזקאל Yechezkel had נבואה nevuah and he
was in בבל. Bavel. So טפח ליה אבוה בסנדליה, tephach lei avueh
be-sandaleih, so his father basically kicked him with his shoe or hit
him with his shoe, smacked him with his shoe. אמר ליה amar
lei and he says to him לאו אמינא לך lav amina lach
haven't I told you לא תטריד עלמא lo tatrid alma don't bother
people don't sort of don't annoy people? מה היה שהיה כבר ma
haya she-haya kvar
what was already was. Now what does that mean? So one version
of this means is that it happened once that doesn't mean it's
a regular occurrence. The רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom gives a fascinating other
interpretation which means that he had already started his נבואה nevuah in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, שהיה כבר, she-haya kvar, since he started his
נבואה nevuah in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he was able to continue
in בבל. Bavel. But basically the point is you know what? Don't
ask קשיות kushyas about a הספד, hesped, okay? That's how I'm going
to interpret the response. During the הספד? hesped? Sounds like it, you
know, maybe or I don't know maybe it was after the הספד
hesped maybe it was like, yeah right, no שכינה Shechina in בבל
Bavel right, how about this? Yeah just shut up we're in the
middle of a הספד. hesped. So anyway okay but yeah was?
Well can I ask a question? I don't think there's anything in
יחזקאל Yechezkel that indicates that he ever reported any prophecies other than
when he was in exile in בבל. Bavel.
I know but alright but it's a תירוץ. teretz. It's not that
there's any evidence to it. Okay. Alright so that was some initial
words that were said to him in בבל Bavel but here they
are they're now transporting the ארון aron to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and he's going to be buried in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay
so כי אתיוהו להתם ki atyuhei le-hatam
when they brought him there meaning to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael אמרו
ליה לרבי אמי ולרבי אסי amru lei le-Rabbi Ami u-le-Rabbi Assi they
said to רב אמי Rav Ami and רב אסי, Rav Assi, רב
הונא אתי, Rav Huna ati, רב הונא Rav Huna is coming. אמרו
amru they said כי הוינן התם ki havinnan tam when we were
there in בבל Bavel לא הוה לן למיזקפי רישין מיניה lo hava
lan lemizkpei reshin mineih we couldn't lift up our heads in his
presence. We were so afraid of him afraid of his, you know,
his תורה Torah anyway maybe he was a scary guy we were
intimidated by him and by his תורה we couldn't lift up our
heads.
Okay so השתא אתינן הכא hashta ateinan hacha אתא בתרן ata batran
now he's coming here and he's coming after us? They thought he
was alive. Oh they said what? He's coming! They didn't say his
coffin is coming they said he's coming they said he's coming we
were scared to death with him in בבל Bavel what is he
doing chasing after us here? So אמרו להו amru lehu no ארונא
הוא דאתי arona hu de-ati no no no his coffin is coming
he's dead. So okay so רבי אמי ורבי אסי נפקי Rabbi Ami
ve-Rabbi Assi nafki so רב אמי Rav Ami and רב אסי Rav
Assi now okay fine he's dead so then they went out to
participate in the funeral, you know, procedure
procession. רבי אילא ורבי חנינא לא נפקי, Rabbi Ila ve-Rabbi Chanina lo
nafki, רב אילא Rav Ila and רב חנינא Rav Chanina did not
go out to the procession. איכא דאמרי ika de-amri some say רבי
אילא נפק רבי חנינא לא נפק Rabbi Ila nafak Rabbi Chanina lo
nafak so some say רב אילא Rav Ila went but רב חנינא
Rav Chanina did not go. You know you think like, okay, you
don't show up at the funeral you don't go up to a
שבעה who's going to really notice? So here you go like two
thousand years later we're still remembering who didn't come to the funeral.
Okay anyway. So דנפקי מאי טעמא de-nafki mai ta'ama what's the reason
of those that went out? דתניא de-tanya we taught in a ברייתא
העובר ממקום למקום ha-over mi-makom le-makom that if a if a coffin
is being transported from place to place, you know, it's being transported
to the place it'll be buried עומדים עליו בשורה ואומרים עליו ברכת
אבלים ותנחומי אבלים omdim alav be-shura ve-omrim alav birkat avelim ve-tanchumei avelim
so where it, you know, at different stops or, you know, you
will the people will participate in a type of a observance
of אבלות or an observance of the burial types of observances. They
will stand in the שורה shura they'll say, you know, the ניחום
nichum to the אבלים avelim and so on. So therefore okay yes
there was some funeral process that happened back in בבל Bavel but
we're going to do that again here.
So דלא נפקי מאי טעמא de-lo nafki mai ta'ama what's the reason
of those that did not come out? דתניא we taught in a
ברייתא ארון העובר ממקום למקום אין עומדים עליו בשורה ואין אומרים עליו
ברכת אבלים ותנחומי אבלים aron ha-over mi-makom le-makom ein omdim alav be-shura
ve-ein omrim alav birkat avelim ve-tanchumei avelim you don't do the funeral
practices again. So the גמרא says קשיא אהדדי kashya ahadadi okay so
these ברייתות braitot contradict. So לא קשיא lo kashya כאן ששלדו קיימת
כאן שאין שלדו קיימת kan she-shildo kayemet kan she-ein shildo kayemet it
matters is the sort of the spine, you know, sort of the
bone form still present or not? Skeleton. Skeleton, thank you. The skeleton
still present? If the skeleton now has turned into like a just
a, you know, unconnected bones, then it's not you would not, you
know, then it's been a while since the person died and you're
not going to do a whole other type of a funeral, you
know, practices. But if the skeleton is still present, even if the
body look, it's not like you put on a plane and twelve
hours later the body's in Israel, right? It takes some time to
get these things. And what and maybe by the way, maybe they
even waited till I don't know, at times maybe they could have
waited like we heard here waiting about transporting till the כוך, kuch,
I'm I'm just speculating, but maybe they waited till the flesh decomposed,
you know, maybe it would be less smelly to transport it once
the flesh had decomposed. So anyway, so it depends how much is
it still like in the process of really like seeming, you know,
that it's appropriate to still do these burial, you know, sort of
rituals. So it depends whether the skeleton is still there or not.
So the גמרא says ושילדא דרב הונא קיימת הוה. v'shilda d'Rav Huna
kayames hava. And the שילדא, shilda, the skeleton, was still there. So
that's why they went out. So דלא נפיק, d'lo nafik, so the
גמרא is saying right. So I'm sorry, that's a question. ושילדא דרב
הונא קיימת הוה? v'shilda d'Rav Huna kayames hava? One
minute. So wasn't his שילדא shilda present? So why did they not
go out? Or a question or statement. But anyway, the question is
implicit if it's not a question itself. Why didn't they go out
if his his skeleton was there? דלא נפיק לא סיימו קמיה. d'lo
nafik lo siymu kamei. Those that did not go out, they didn't
sort of finish it to them, they didn't explain that he was
still the skeleton was still present and it was still appropriate to
to participate. They didn't realize those were the circumstances. Now, let's keep
on going. אמרי היכא נינחיה. amri heicha ninchei. Okay. So they brought
him there and they did some funeral practice rituals. Some people had
a misinformation but anyway they did some funeral rituals and now they're
getting ready to bury him. Okay. אמרי היכא
נינחיה, amri heicha ninchei, where should we bury him? Where should we
place him?
רב הונא ריביץ תורה בישראל רב חייא ריביץ תורה בישראל. Rav Huna
reibitz Torah b'Yisrael, Rav Chiya reibitz Torah b'Yisrael. Rav Huna taught Torah
in Israel, and Rav Chiya not just taught like sort of, you
know, spread it like was, you know, sort of really made sure
that it would get taught very widely. And Rav Chiya disseminated, thank
you, ריביץ תורה בישראל. reibitz Torah b'Yisrael. These people remember the famous
story about Rabbi Chiya, right? That he basically, you know, he said,
I would make I'm going to make sure that Torah would never
get lost from Israel, you know, and he sort of, you know,
he made all these ספר תורה Sefer Torah scrolls and he distributed
them to all these cities and he taught, you know, people to
like learn learn your portion and teach one another a portion and
he sort of set up this whole system that also was very
empowering for the for the learners that the learners became teachers and
so on to make sure that like Torah would be very widely
disseminated. Okay? So both of these disseminated Torah in Israel הוי. havei.
So we should bury him next to Rabbi Chiya. מאן מעייל ליה?
man ma'ayel lei?
So now who's going to bring him into the into the cave
where Rabbi Chiya is buried? Because there was this whole idea, right?
That where great sages were buried and their caves and it was
protected and so on. So אמר להו רב חגא. amar lehu Rav
Chaga. Rav Chaga said, אנא מעיילנא ליה. ana ma'ayilna lei. I'll bring
him into the cave. דאוקמתיה לתלמודאי d'ukmaseih l'talmudei כי הוינא בר תמני
סרי שנין. ki havina bar tamnei srei shanin. First of all, I
established my teaching presumably in front of him. This would be some
type of phenomenon that a student would tell over or like all
of the things that he had learned and memorized and all of,
you know, in front of a in front of his רבי. So
I basically did that for him when I was just eighteen years
old. So ולא חזאי לי קרי. v'lo chazai li keri. And I
never had a seminal emission. ומשמשי ליה קמיה. u'meshamshi lei kamei. And
I was his attendant. וידעינא בעובדיה. v'yada'ina b'uvdeih. And I know his
his great deed.
So meaning sort of like saying two things. Number one is I'm
a really good guy, so they'll let me, the spirits or whatever
the powers that protect the cave will let me into the cave.
And number two, I have a very I have a very intimate
relationship with him and I'm the appropriate person therefore to be involved
in this. Okay. And I know his deed. דיומא חד אפיך ליה
רצועה דתפילין. d'yoma chad afich lei retzu'ah d'tefillin. One day I'll tell
you what a צדיק tzadik he was, that one day the strap
of his תפילין tefillin sort of, you know, reversed itself and the
white was exposed on the outside and the black on the inside.
ויתיב עליה ארבעין תעניתא. v'yasiv alei arba'in ta'anisa. So
and he he fasted forty forty fasts because of that. I don't
know. Okay. Anyway, so this is what they're doing. עייליה. ayilei. So
they brought him into the cave. הוה גני יהודה מימיניה דאבוה וחזקיה
משמאליה. hava gani Yehuda mimineih d'avuah v'Chizkiya mismaleih.
So Rabbi Chiya has two sons, יהודה Yehuda and חזקיה. Chizkiya. And
they were both buried together with him, one on his right and
one on his left. So now they are going to be reanimated.
Okay. So אמר ליה יהודה לחזקיה. amar lei Yehuda l'Chizkiya. So
יהודה Yehuda said to חזקיה. Chizkiya. These are both, you understand, buried
and dead near their father. קום מדוכתך. kum miduchach. Get up from
your place. דלאו ארח ארעא דקאי רב הונא
בהדן. d'lav orach ara d'ka'i Rav Huna behadan. That it's not דרך
ארץ derech eretz that Rav Huna should be standing standing among us.
Now, what does that mean? Why is Rav Huna standing? Wouldn't they
be lying him down? So it's a very difficult text. רבינו גרשום
Rabbeinu Gershom has the and not רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, רבינו חננאל's
Rabbeinu Chananel text is דלאו ארח ארעא דקאי רב הונא מבראי. d'lav
orach ara d'ka'i Rav Huna mibara'i. That it's not appropriate that he
is on the outside. Meaning, we have to move over to make
room for him. It's not he should be
or he should be
on... cave, we have to
whatever. Anyway, according to רבינו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel*, at least you understand
it a little bit more. He's still outside. We have to move
because it's not appropriate for him to be outside. Okay, so בהדי
דקאי *Bahadei d'ka'ei*, as they were getting up or the other one
was getting up, who says to who? יהודה *Yehuda* says to חזקיה
*Chizkiya*. As חזקיה *Chizkiya* was getting up, קמה בהדי עמודא דנורא *Kama
bahadei amuda d'nura*. So, a pillar of fire rose together with חזקיה
*Chizkiya*. Okay. חזא רב חגא *Chaza Rav Chaga*, so רב חגא *Rav
Chaga* saw this pillar of fire coming from within the cave. So,
איבעית *Ivis*, he got scared. זקפיה לארונא *Zakfei l'arona*, he stood up
the ארון *Aron*. ונפק *Ve'nafik*, and he ran away. Okay, so presumably
the ארון *Aron* was never buried in the cave, it was somehow
left standing or left unburied, which would seem to be a real
problem. But the גמרא *Gemara* says והאי דלא איענש איענש *v'hai d'lo
i-anish anish* and the fact that he wasn't punished, now who, רב
חגא *Rav Chaga*, or he wasn't hurt by the fire, presumably משום
דזקפיה לארונא דרב הונא *mishum d'zakfei l'arona d'Rav Huna* because he put
up the ארון *Aron*. But what does that exactly mean? I mean,
he should have buried him. What does it mean he wasn't punished?
And some understand it means like he put up the ארון *Aron*
to protect him from the fire. Like, you know, here's a big
fire coming at you, you put the ארון *Aron* and, you know,
between the wall and you run away, so then why wasn't he
punished? That's very hard to understand.
This guy said he was so appropriate.
Yeah, so
it's very confusing. I haven't found much discussion on it. I will
tell you that רבינו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* says, has again his גרסא
*girsa* is האי דלא איענש דבי נשיאה *hai d'lo i-anish d'vei nesi'ah*,
because רב הונא *Rav Huna* was a descendant of the בית הנשיא
*Beis hanasi* of and that'll come up in a later sort of
thing in a later story as well. And so somehow it means
like the reason that there's this special זכות *zechus* that the בית
הנשיא *Beis hanasi* has that they are protected is because of what
רב הונא *Rav Huna* what רב חגא *Rav Chaga* did with the
ארון *Aron*. But it still doesn't explain why was that a good
thing, what he did with the ארון *Aron*?
The reason why the ארון *Aron* wasn't burned?
No, no. That the reason that the בית הנשיא *Beis hanasi* in
the future is protected is because of what רב חגא *Rav Chaga*
did. Okay.
Let's just do one more line, we'll have to finish this tomorrow.
So it says like this, כי נח נפשיה *ki nach nafshai*, oh
you know what, we're done with רב הונא *Rav Huna*. So we
will pick up I guess with this tomorrow, we'll leave some of
the really beautiful eulogies, we'll see them tomorrow. Okay.